A Guide to the Nelson A. Rockefeller personal papers, Politics - Oscar M. Ruebhausen, Series J.3 FA347
Rockefeller Archive Center
Nelson A. Rockefeller personal papers, Politics - Oscar M. Ruebhausen, Series J.3
1967-1970
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ruebhausen, Oscar M.
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich)
Molitor, Graham T. T. (Graham Thomas Tate)
FA347
3.49 Cubic Feet 5 legal document boxes, 3 letter document boxes.
Biographical/Historical note
Nelson Aldrich Rockefeller was born on July 8, 1908, in Bar Harbor, Maine, the third child of John Davison Rockefeller, Jr., and Abby Aldrich Rockefeller. He graduated from the Lincoln School of Teachers College at Columbia University in New York City in 1926. Mr. Rockefeller attended Dartmouth College where he was elected to Phi Beta Kappa, graduating cum laude in 1930 with an A.B. degree in economics.
After college, Mr. Rockefeller was active in family enterprises, including real estate, banking, and family philanthropies. His major business interests in time became focused on Rockefeller Center and Latin America. In 1938, he became the president of Rockefeller Center.
In 1935, because of his interest in national affairs and his desire to learn about U.S. business abroad, Mr. Rockefeller became a director of Creole Petroleum Company, the Venezuelan subsidiary of Standard Oil of New Jersey. This association led eventually to his deep, life-long interest in Latin America. He made extensive visits to Latin America in 1937 and 1939 to study economic, social, and political conditions. He resigned his directorship in the Creole Petroleum Company in 1940.
In 1940, Mr. Rockefeller and his four brothers organized the Rockefeller Brothers Fund to carry out a broad range of philanthropic activities.
Throughout his life Mr. Rockefeller was an avid supporter of the arts. He served as a trustee, treasurer, president, and chair of the board of the Museum of Modern Art, which was cofounded by his mother. In 1954, he founded the Museum of Primitive Art, which collected of indigenous art of the Americas, Africa, Oceania, and early Asia and Europe.
After his 1939 visit to Latin America, Mr. Rockefeller prepared a memorandum for President Franklin D. Roosevelt outlining his deep concern over Nazi influence and penetration into that part of the world. In the memo he recommended a U.S. program of cooperation with the nations of the western hemisphere to achieve better relations among these nations and to help raise their standards of living. Largely as a result of this memo, President Roosevelt asked Mr. Rockefeller in August of 1940 to initiate and head a new program ultimately known as the Office of Inter-American Affairs. Mr. Rockefeller served as Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs, his first full-time position in public service.
Mr. Rockefeller served in this position until December 1944, when President Roosevelt appointed him Assistant Secretary of State for American Republic Affairs. In this post, Mr. Rockefeller initiated the Inter-American Conference on Problems of War and Peace in Mexico City in February of 1945. It resulted in the Act of Chapultepec, which provided the framework for economic, social, and defense cooperation among the nations of the western hemisphere and set the principle that an attack on one of these nations would be regarded as an attack on all and jointly resisted.
Mr. Rockefeller signed the Act of Chapultepec on behalf of the United States. He also attended the United Nations Conference on International Organization in San Francisco in 1945. At the conference, there was considerable opposition to the idea of permitting, within the UN Charter, the formation of regional pacts such as the Act of Chapultepec. Mr. Rockefeller, who believed that the inclusion was essential, especially to U.S. policy in Latin America, successfully argued the need for regional pacts within the framework of the United Nations. The importance of this victory was underscored by the subsequent formation of NATO, SEATO, and the Rio Pact.
During these war-time years, Mr. Rockefeller also served as Chairman of the Inter-American Development Commission, which was established in June 1940 to reorganize and revitalize Latin American economies following the loss of European markets. He was also the U.S. Co-Chairman of the Mexican-American Development Commission to help Mexico emerge as an industrial nation in the transition from war to peace.
Mr. Rockefeller resigned as Assistant Secretary of State on August 24, 1945.
Upon his return to private life in New York in 1946, Mr. Rockefeller became chair of the board of Rockefeller Center and undertook a program of physical expansion. Two other initiatives during this period illustrate Mr. Rockefeller's continuing interest in Latin America and international economic development. In July of 1946, the Rockefeller brothers established a philanthropic organization, the American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA). AIA financed nonprofit projects to ameliorate health, educational, agricultural, and other social problems in the poorer areas of Latin America. Nelson Rockefeller served as President from July 1946 to June 1953 and from January 1957 to December 1958. In 1947, he organized the International Basic Economy Corporation (IBEC), a business corporation to help raise living standards in foreign countries through new economic enterprises. In its early years, IBEC concentrated on enterprises in Latin America but later expanded its activities to other regions. Mr. Rockefeller served as IBEC President from January 1947 to June 1953 and from January 1956 to December 1958.
In his inaugural address in January 1949, President Harry S. Truman announced the Point IV program for providing technical assistance to developing nations. This concept was based in part on programs Mr. Rockefeller and his associates had developed through the Office of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs and the private, philanthropic AIA. In November of 1950, President Truman asked Mr. Rockefeller to serve as Chairman of the International Development Advisory Board. The Board was charged with recommending policies for carrying out the Point IV program. The Board's report, entitled "Partners in Progress," provided the basic blueprint for America's foreign assistance program.
On November 20, 1952, President-elect Dwight D. Eisenhower asked Mr. Rockefeller to serve as Chairman of the President's Advisory Committee on Government Organization, a group created to recommend ways to improve the efficiency of the executive branch of the government. As Chairman of that committee, Mr. Rockefeller recommended 13 reorganization plans to the President, 10 of which were approved by Congress. These plans achieved basic changes in the organization of the Department of Defense, the Department of Agriculture, and the Office of Defense Mobilization, among others. Another of the plans led to the establishment of the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare. In June 1953, Mr. Rockefeller was appointed Under Secretary of the new department. He was especially active in the department's legislative program, recommending measures that covered an additional ten million people under the Social Security program. He resigned as HEW Under Secretary in 1954 to become Special Assistant to the President for Foreign Affairs.
While serving as Special Assistant, Mr. Rockefeller played a key role in the development of the "Open Skies" proposal for checking on world armaments through mutual air reconnaissance. He accompanied President Eisenhower to the Geneva Summit Conference in 1955, where the plan was proposed to the world by the President. Mr. Rockefeller resigned as Special Assistant on December 31, 1955.
Mr. Rockefeller first ran for public office in 1958 and was elected Governor of New York on November 4, defeating incumbent Averill Harriman. He took office January 1, 1959, and was subsequently re-elected Governor three more times, thus becoming the first Governor in the nation's history to be elected to four 4-year terms.
Nelson Rockefeller's tenure as a public servant in the federal government was a formative period in his life. By the time he left Washington to assume the governorship of New York, he had received a thorough education in the workings of the federal government. His chairmanship of PACGO permitted him to examine every aspect of the executive branch. This and his work in HEW exposed him to a wide variety of domestic issues. He gained experience in initiating legislation, in foreign policy and diplomacy, in domestic and international economics, and in national security and military affairs. In the process he also received an education in national politics and gained a reputation for being an effective and hardworking administrator. Most importantly, these appointments provided him with the opportunity to form the friendships and personal associations that served him throughout his political career.
Mr. Rockefeller resigned as Governor of New York in December 1973. In August 1974, President Gerald R. Ford nominated him to fill the vacant vice presidency following the resignation of President Richard M. Nixon. Mr. Rockefeller served as Vice President from December 19, 1974, to January 20, 1977. Nelson Rockefeller died on January 26, 1979, in New York City.
File Plan note
Former Classification: III 04 J.3
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Material in the Rockefeller family collections that provides the names, correspondence, or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net wealth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Arrangement note
There are four subseries in this series:
Subseries 1 - Current Issues, 1968
Subseries 2 - NAR Political, 1968
Subseries 3 - OMR General, 1968
Subseries 4 - Notebooks and Reports, 1967-1970
Scope and Contents note
This series contains a portion of the files of Oscar M. Ruebhausen. They were created primarily during Ruebhausen's service as head of DNA, a research organization for Nelson Rockefeller that was founded by Roswell Perkins. Ruebhausen headed DNA during Governor Rockefeller's run for the Republican presidential nomination in 1968. Some of the materials also cover Rockefeller's gubernatorial reelection campaign in 1970. The majority of these documents may also be found in other series specifically Rockefeller's personal papers, DNA, Series G and Rockefeller's Gubernatorial records, Issue Books, Series 17.
This series contains the office files of Oscar M. Ruebhausen. They document his official activities as a member of Nelson A. Rockefeller's staff. The actions, decisions, and exchanges of information or points of view documented here occurred in the course of proposing and implementing policies for the Rockefeller administration, the political campaigns, and/or Rockefeller's personal activities. However, unless a document is personally signed by Nelson A. Rockefeller, or is referred to in a document personally signed by him, it should not be assumed he saw the document or was aware of its existence or substance. Furthermore, researchers should bear in mind that staff files may contain documents or drafts addressed to Rockefeller that were never shown to him.
Other Finding Aids note
Detailed finding aids for each series of this collection are available:
Nelson A. Rockefeller papers, Activities (FA338)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, AIA-IBEC (FA339)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Art (FA340)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Countries (FA341)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, DNA (FA342)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Family and Friends (FA343)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Oral Histories (FA344)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Politics - New York City Office (FA345)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Politics - George L. Hinman (FA346)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Projects (FA348)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Speeches, Post-Vice Presidential (FA349)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Washington, DC (FA350)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Ann C. Whitman - Politics (FA351)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Hugh Morrow Interviews (FA352)
Art, Primitive; Arts; Brazil; Business; Business enterprises, Foreign; Civic improvement; Civics; Developing countries; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1962; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1958; Government policy; Government agencies; Federal government -- United States; Education -- Latin America; Agriculture; Agriculture -- Latin America; Philanthropy -- United States; International relations -- United States; Latin America; International economic relations; International relations; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1966; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1970; Philanthropy -- New York (N.Y.); Philanthropy; Venezuela; Philanthropy -- New York (State); United States; State governments -- United States; New York (N.Y.); New York (State); Education; National security -- United States; Economic policy; Economics; Public health -- Latin America; Social problems -- Latin America; Presidential campaigns -- United States; Presidential candidates -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Political campaigns -- United States; Political science
- Current Issues, 1968; 1; 1 Cubic Feet
  Arrangement note
  Subseries 1 is arranged alphabetically by issue.
  Scope and Contents note
  This subseries is primarily files created by the research staff of DNA for the 1968 presidential campaign. The files comprise reports and position papers as well as memoranda and correspondence with outside sources offering expert advice on issues.
  - Agriculture (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Agriculture (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Indians (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Civil Rights (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Consumer Protection (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Crime (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Economy (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Education (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Federalism (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Foreign Policy (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Health (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Housing (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Issue Summaries (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Collected position papers on variety of political issues.
  - Judicial (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Labor (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Latin America (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - LBJ and the Great Society (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Natural Resources (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Poverty (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Presidency (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Science (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Social Issues (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Urban Issues (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Vietnam (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Welfare (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Youth (Box 3, Folder 26)
- NAR Political, 1968; 2; 0.6 Cubic Feet
  These files date primarily from May through July 1968, when Nelson Rockefeller was actively pursuing the Republican presidential nomination. The files contain a variety of political information and advice given to Oscar Ruebhausen in his role as head of DNA or offered directly to Rockefeller, either by or through Ruebhausen. Of particular interest in this subseries are memoranda on how Rockefeller might go on to win the general election if he was successful in gaining the Republican nomination.
  - Candidate Debate, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    Correspondence and memoranda surrounding NAR open offer to debate Richard Nixon and other presidential candidates in a debate.
  - Convention, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    Pre-convention "checklist," other memoranda and clippings on NAR plans at Republican convention in Miami, Florida.
  - Letters Written for the Governor, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    Draft replies and correspondence to various organizations that had written to NAR asking for his views on the presidency.
  - Mailings, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    "Rockefeller for President" and "New York Citizens for Rockefeller for President" correspondence on behalf of the campaign, urging support for NAR.
  - National Election, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    Correspondence and clippings surrounding concerns of a deadlock in the Electoral College, based on the candidacy of Governor George Wallace.
  - News Coverage, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    Copies of newspaper clippings on political campaigns and activities of candidates.
  - Nixon, Richard M., 1968 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    Correspondence, memoranda, clippings, notes on the Richard M. Nixon candidacy and the Rockefeller campaign's response.
  - Other Candidates, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    Correspondence, memoranda, clippings, notes on the activities of the other presidential candidates, including Senator Eugene McCarthy, Governor Ronald Reagan, and Senator Robert Kennedy.
  - Pamphlets, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    Selection of campaign literature used by the Rockefeller campaign in the 1968 presidential season.
  - Platform, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    Policy papers for use on committee to draft Republican platform.
  - Post-Nomination, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    Memo from Oscar M. Ruebhausen to NAR on vice presidential selection possibilities, George L. Hinman memo on strategy for NAR if successful in garnering the Republican nomination.
  - Public Opinion, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    Correspondence and selection of polling information on NAR campaign.
  - Rockefeller Record, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    Selections of NAR statements used in the campaign piece, "The Rockefeller Record."
  - Schedule, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    Memorandum from the "Scheduling Committee" reviewing NAR's pending invitations based on the national campaign.
  - Speeches, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    Drafts, press releases, transcripts of selected NAR speeches on various issues.
  - Themes, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    Memoranda and correspondence on various themes that could be utilized by the campaign to attract voters.
  - Voter Registration, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    Memorandum on percentages of population registered to the two main political parties from 1956 through 1966.
- OMR General, 1968; 3; 0.4 Cubic Feet
  This small subseries is entirely office memoranda and correspondence concerning Ruebhausen's tenure as head of DNA in 1968.
  - Correspondence, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    Oscar M. Ruebhausen correspondence with selected individuals offering perspective of NAR candidacy and Oscar M. Ruebhausen urging of support of Republican ticket.
  - DNA Organization, Staff, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 45)
    Office memoranda on day-to-day operations of running of DNA offices.
  - DNA Personnel, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 46)
    Memoranda and correspondence on individuals working on DNA in spring 1968.
  - Miscellaneous, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 47)
    Campaign archive material from Saville Ryan, primarily letters from NAR to various organizations congratulating them on achievements, holding meetings, anniversaries, etc.
  - Miscellaneous, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Miscellaneous, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Notes, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 50)
    Oscar M. Ruebhausen notes on issues of campaign.
- Notebooks and Reports, 1967-1970; 4; 1.2 Cubic Feet
  The final subseries consists of materials accumulated by DNA staff and the Answer Desk, a research group headed by Graham Molitor to assist with the Presidential campaign. Also found in this subseries are two general issues polls of New York voters undertaken prior to the 1970 gubernatorial reelection of Nelson Rockefeller.
  - Answer Desk Profile on Richard Nixon, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 51)
    Comprehensive profile of Nixon compiled by DNA research staff. Chapter titles: "Loser Image"; "Political Image: Tricky Dick"; "Personality: The Unstable Man"; "Everybody on Nixon"; "Campaign Style"; "Nixon: Unqualified for President."
  - Answer Desk Profile on Richard Nixon, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 52)
  - Answer Desk Profile on Richard Nixon, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 53)
  - Answer Desk Profile on Richard Nixon, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - "The Challenge of Crime in a Free Society" (Box 6, Folder 55)
    February 1967 report by the President's Commission on Law Enforcement and Administration of Justice.
  - Domestic Research Staff - Recommended Position Papers, May 30, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 56)
    Indexed position papers on domestic issues prepared by DNA staff.
  - Domestic Research Staff - Recommended Position Papers, May 31, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 57)
  - Fact Sheets on Foreign Policy, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 58)
    Indexed position papers on foreign policy issues prepared by DNA staff.
  - Foreign Policy Comparisons of Candidate Positions (Box 7, Folder 59)
    Summary positions on foreign policy held by Nelson Rockefeller, Richard Nixon, and the other GOP candidates.
  - Nixon on Civil Rights, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 60)
    Briefing book, which includes a general position paper on civil rights record. Includes memos on Nixon's major weaknesses and suggest possible means for exploiting them. Prepared by Answer Desk, Graham T. T. Molitor, Director. Chapter titles: "Southern Strategy"; "Open Housing"; "Busing"; "Riots"; "Rebuilding the Ghetto."
  - "Political Opinion in New York State" (Box 7, Folder 61)
    Poll conducted by Political Surveys and Analyses, Inc., interviews conducted in late April and Early May 1970.
  - "Political Opinion in New York State" (Box 7, Folder 62)
  - "Poll Data About Gubernatorial Candidates" (Box 7, Folder 63)
    Poll conducted by Political Surveys and Analyses, Inc., interviews conducted in late July and early August 1970.
  - "Poll Data About Gubernatorial Candidates" (Box 7, Folder 64)
  - Positions on the Issues, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 65)
    Published brochures, statements, speeches, press releases, internal memoranda on the positions held on national issues by the major candidates for Presidency in 1968, including Hubert Humphrey, Robert Kennedy, Ronald Reagan, Richard Nixon.
  - Positions on the Issues, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 66)
  - Positions on the Issues, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 67)
  - Positions on the Issues, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 68)
  - "The Rockefeller Strategy" (Box 8, Folder 69)
    Research and intelligence report with a plan to win the 1968 Republican nomination, April 18, 1968.
  - "The Summer Campaign" (Box 8, Folder 70)
    Research and intelligence report on the Rockefeller candidacy and Republican politics, April-May 1968, May 28, 1968.
  - Trip: Kansas, May 7, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 71)
    Oscar M. Ruebhausen travel book on NAR political trip to the state.
  - Trip: Minnesota, May 8, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 72)